Guide to the Charles Downing Lay Papers 1865-1966 PR 366
New-York Historical Society
Charles Downing Lay papers
1865-1966
New-York Historical Society
Lay, Charles Downing, 1877-1956
PR 366
3.0 Linear feet in two boxes and one folder
This collection consists of material by and related to the American landscape architect Charles Downing Lay (1877-1956). It includes correspondence, landscape architecture drawings, lectures, printed materials, photographs, engravings, and watercolors.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 7 series by document type.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Downing Lay (1877-1956) was an early 20th century landscape architect. The son of painter Oliver Ingraham Lay and Hester Marian Wait Lay, he was born in Newburgh, New York on Sept. 3, 1877. Lay attended Columbia University's School of Architecture from 1896 to 1900, and in 1902 became the second graduate of the landscape architecture program at Harvard University.
In 1904, Lay started his own landscape architecture practice, and in 1910, he formed a partnership with Henry V. Hubbard and Robert Wheelwright. They practiced under the name Lay, Hubbard, and Wheelwright and in October 1910 they began publishing the professional journal Landscape Architecture, with Lay serving as editor and manager until 1921.
Lay worked as the landscape architect for the New York City Department of Parks from 1913 to 1914. He was later hired by the City of New York to design Alley Pond Park in Queens in 1929. Lay's design of Marine Park in Brooklyn (which was never fully realized) won a silver medal at the 1936 Berlin Olympics.
Lay was the consulting landscape architect to the board of design for the 1939 New York World's Fair. During World War II Lay worked on such military projects as Fort Jay in Brooklyn, New York, and the naval air station at Floyd Bennett Field. After the war he consulted for the U.S. and New York City Public Housing Authorities.
Lay contributed to a variety of publications, writing extensively on such topics as parks, urban planning, art, and architecture. He was a fellow of the American Society of Landscape Architects, and member of the National Academy of Design, the Art Students League of New York, and the Century Association. In 1948 he helped form the Housatonic Valley Planning Association.
Lay died on Feb. 15, 1956 in Stratford, Connecticut at the age of 78.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase, 2015.
Related Materials
The New-York Historical Society's Manuscript department holds two related items: Charles Downing Lay, Blueprint, 1947 (AHMC Lay, Charles Downing) and Oliver Ingraham Lay, notebook, 1861-1889 (BV Lay)
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of material by and related to the American landscape architect Charles Downing Lay (1877-1956). It includes correspondence, landscape architecture drawings, lectures, printed materials, photographs, engravings, and watercolors.
Architectural drawings (visual works); Engravings (prints); Letters (correspondence); Watercolors (paintings); Landscape architecture -- United States; Lay, Charles Downing, 1877-1956; Lay, Oliver Ingraham, 1845-1890; Century Association (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I: Architectural plans, 1939-1950
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains 6 landscape architecture design drawings by Charles Downing Lay and Associates.
  Related Materials
  In Manuscripts Collection: Charles Downing. Blueprint of the landscape design plan for the estate of Frank J. Mann in New Castle, N.Y. Designed by Charles Downing Lay on Feb. 3, 1947; revised March 31, 1947. (AHMC Lay, Charles Downing)
  - Planting plan for Krider Nurseries Rock Garden, Horticultural Exhibition, New York World's Fair, 1939 (Folder FF 1)
  - Lordship Community Church Planting Plan, 1950 (Folder FF 1)
  - Set of 4 landscape plans for the Scintilla Magneto Division of the Bendix Aviation Corporation in Sidney, NY, 1940 (Folder FF 1)
- Series II: Artwork, 1865-1934
  This series includes watercolors and engravings, mostly landscapes and still lifes, with a few portraits. The bulk of the artwork is by Charles Downing Lay, but there are also works by other artists, including Lay's father, Oliver Ingraham Lay, and Lay's wife, Laura Gill Lay. Some works are unsigned.
  - Paintings by Charles Downing Lay, 1925-1927 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Paintings by Charles Downing Lay, 1930-1934 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Paintings by other artists, 1865-1926 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Paintings, unsigned, 1925, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Prints by Charles Downing Lay, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Prints by other artists, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Prints by Charles Downing Lay, 1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1910-1945
  This series consists of letters to and from Lay. Correspondents include Charles Dana Gibson (1943-44); Bertram Grosvenor Goodhue (1919-24); Robert Moses (1922); Frederick Law Olmsted Jr. (1913, 1917); John C. Olmsted (1913); and Augustus Vincent Tack (1940-44).
  The bulk of the correspondence has to do with Lay's involvement with the Century Association. There are many invitations and responses to dinners and exhibitions at the club.
  There is also a substantial amount of correspondence with and about the architect Bertram Grosvenor Goodhue. There are letters between Lay and Goodhue discussing a mutual project (the Myler House in Pittsburgh), and then, after Goodhue's death in 1924, correspondence about planning a memorial exhibition of Goodhue's work at the Century Association.
  There are also two letters from 1910 discussing the idea for the journal Landscape Architecture, as well as a letter appointing Lay the Landscape Architect of the NYC Department of Parks.
  - Correspondence, 1910-1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1919-1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Photographs, 1925, undated
  This series contains 20 photographs, mostly undated. It includes 7 images of George M. Olcott's estate, Casagmo, in Ridgefield, CT, which was designed by Lay. There is also one photo of architects working at drafting tables.
  - Photographs, 1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series V: Printed material, 1916-1965
  This series consists of exhibition catalogs, including one for the Horticultural Exhibition at the 1939 World's Fair; brochures about artists and landscapes; printed materials from events held at the Century Association; and miscellaneous clippings.
  - Century Association - Landscape Architecture magazine dinner, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Century Association - Augustus V. Tack dinner, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Century Association - Royal Cortissoz dinner, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Century Association - miscellaneous papers, 1939-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, 1939-1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Exhibitions, 1913, 1961, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Pamphlets, 1916-1958 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series VI: Professional papers, 1906-1939
  This series includes lectures on landscape architecture (unsigned but presumably by Lay); greeting cards and promotional materials from Lay's professional practice; a catalog from a 1925 exhibition featuring Lay's landscape architecture plans and photographs; a certificate from the American Society of Landscape Architects; and a membership card from the Art Students League of New York.
  - Lectures, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Business ephemera, 1906-1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series VII: Ribbons, 1887-1890
  This series includes 9 political and Civil War veteran ribbons. The connection of these items to Lay is unclear.
  - Ribbons, 1887-1890 (Box 1, Folder 19)